this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this episode of software
engineering radio is sponsored by data
dog data dog is a monitoring platform
that helps thousands of companies get
visibility into cloud infrastructure
optimized application performance and
avoid downtime data dog integrates with
more than 200 technologies so you can
get immediate insights into all of your
databases your web servers cloud
services and container technologies like
docker and kubernetes start a free trial
today at dado dog comm / se radio hi
this is Elena Salinas for software
engineering radio today
Asaf Yigal is joining us from Israel
Asaf is co-founder at logs IO a platform
powered by artificial intelligence that
analyzes logs prior to this he
co-founded a social trading platform and
worked in executive roles developing an
end-to-end performance monitoring
platform I will be talking with Asaf
about the log analysis process and the
role of machine learning and humans in
this for an introduction to machine
learning check out episode two eight six
titled intro to machine learning Asaf
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you very much for having me you
work on a platform for log analysis that
uses machine learning we did an episode
on logging and logging infrastructure
episode 220 what information do logs
have it really depends on on the
information that the customer or the
engineer organization sends
most and most common thing log data
includes the operational of how the
system is performing when is every
process thread starts and everything
that goes along with it it's basically
very custom and in developers write
their own their own lobs to the log
files mm-hmm and for your product
what definition of machine learning and
artificial intelligence are you using so
what we do and when we started a company
we realized that one of the biggest
challenges in Logan oolitic is
understanding what is actually
interesting in the log data so
organization sends and save and store
terabytes and terabytes of data on a
daily basis and the biggest question is
obviously no one's going to go through
like no human being is gonna get read
line by line and understand what is
actually interesting in the data and how
do I know that I'm not missing something
which is important obviously most Logan
analytics systems are being used today
for forensics and troubleshooting which
actually indicates that the problem
presented themselves in the log before
it presented themselves somewhere else
because the log provide all the
troubleshooting forensics information
and the biggest question that we ask
yourself is how do we find interesting
information in the data and we looked at
a bunch of different methods of doing it
and the way we decided to do it is
instead of looking at the actual data
we're looking at how people interact
with data which means that what we do is
we crawl the web for every discussion
ever created around log data so we scan
different forums and server fault in
Google Groups and Cora and all these
different places and we use machine
learning to understand okay is this
thread discussing something which exists
in the log which product does they
discussed how severe is the problem
which version is it using is there a
solution in the page in the
thread is the solution satisfactory to
the person who asked the question we
mine all these data and we group all the
threads that talk about the same issue
together and we came up with the
cognitive insights which is a collection
of tens of tens of thousands of
different signature meaning if this hat
you see this in your log file this is
the issuer this is the error this is the
severity and here's a here's a few links
to what is actually interesting in the
data and we've also developed a
technology that can run and correlate
and query all this information on your
data in real time is the data passes
through so the way we analyze if things
are important to to an organization is
by using machine learning to analyze
whether this information was ever useful
or this was actually an issue for other
organizations and your approach is about
combining machine learning with those
human insights yes the way with the way
we do it and the way we think about it
is obviously no human being is going to
go through each one of the logins and
understand what's important the other
alternative of running a black box and
saying we'll try to find patterns try to
find something like that the biggest
issue with that is that there's a lot of
false positives meaning that if you look
at anomalies in IT environment the
entire IT environment is one big anomaly
every version releases is an anomaly
every new customer joining is an anomaly
and anomalies are not always indicated
indicate an issue and issues not
necessarily present themselves as
anomaly so we were taking the human
intelligence which is what people
interact between themselves on the
public domain and in our platform and we
combine that with machine power to be
able to scan tens of thousands of
different issues in real time on your
log data so that's kind of like our
combination of the human intelligence
and machine power to come up with
machine learning and artificial
intelligence to be able to say hey
you've sent us like a terabyte of data
here are five things in the log file you
you know about here's an issue you have
and you have a problem in your SQL and
you have something that's not configured
right in your server and all of this we
do it obviously automatically yeah and
one another example of an anomaly and a
human inside B for for example Black
Friday where it spikes a lot of sales
yeah definitely that's an anomaly which
is not an actual that's not a problem
everybody expects Black Friday to spike
the cells and and that's fine annex and
expected and that's kind of like the
thing is this is one of the reason we're
we've tried out and we believe that
doing a black box anomaly while
mathematically possible yeah its value
is limited I want to understand more the
challenges in log analysis as you
mentioned earlier the information logs
has varies from company to company and
there can be multiple formats for logs
what are examples of the multiple
formats yeah so I think the first
challenge of log analysis and this is
how we start a companies how do I get
all the logs and aggregate in and
normalize them in one location
every log like you said it comes from a
different system that sends in a
different protocol that is behind
firewall not behind firewall needs to
keep the data secure and encrypted
doesn't it to keep the data secure and
encrypted keep a different format a
different date format different fields
in the log data and in right now all the
process is being done on a manual basis
so a person an engineer needs to be able
to go to each one of the system that is
using and configure it to send locks at
the right location configure the parsing
and the data interaction and the
relationship between the data all of it
needs to be done in a manual way and
that's kind of like that's one challenge
it's actually it's it's a pretty big
challenge the second challenge is is
what to do with the data which is what
we talked about with AI in the machine
learning what we the way we address the
the
we've as we've taken the most common log
analytic solution today which is ALK
elasticsearch log stash in Cabana and we
offer it as a cloud service with
enterprise grades with automatic data
parsing with a bunch of other feature
which which are required to in order to
build a Logan oolitic solution and the e
lk that you mentioned is that for the
step where a human is connecting the
different log streams yes bian que is is
basically where the humans connect all
the log stream I mean our service looks
at you always is an LK is a cloud
service that is a LK it's built out of
three components log stash which is the
L in the LK which does the data parsing
and where the human configures the data
structure of each one of the log types
the elasticsearch which is the e which
is a search database it's being used for
many many purposes one of them is Logan
a latex in Cabana which is the K which
is a visualization there and you can
create graphs you can run their searches
from cabana and you can create your own
dashboards and that's kind of like
basically the stack that people used
it's completely open-source and we run
it as a cloud service and the people
involved in this part of the process
what programming or analysis skills are
required to extract the information from
logs to involve the you're talking about
the people that configure the system to
be able to attract a lot or the people
that we have that build the machine
learning and the required the people
that are involved in looking at the logs
and finding relations with them and just
aggregating them right so so the way so
it's very it's a very interesting
question and we do see different
different personas within the
organization treat the logs in different
ways there's the section of the devil
mainly the operational people people
that are responsible to making sure that
the system is up and running what they
care about is is taking the logs in and
to be able to create dashboards and
alert and extracting information in a
visual way to help them monitor the
system the health of the system so this
is one class of the users and they use
it in a very certain way the second
level of people is like the developers
and the developer actually go through
the log lines and understand what's
going on so usually what happens is the
dev ops or an operation engineer or a
site reliability engineer and say hey
we're getting too many error of this can
someone please take a look at it and
because he ran an aggregation that gives
him a list of all the errors and a
developer is going to look at that
specific point of time is going to look
at the services that he is running he's
gonna route read the load line by line
and he's gonna be the one who actually
understands what's going on in in the
log data but it's differently I mean
today especially for organization that
run in the cloud especially for
organization that run in a docker
serverless environment where the
environment is so dynamic and changes
all the time if you did not aggregate
the logs into a centralized location at
the point of creation then your chances
of actually troubleshooting an issue are
zero because most likely the data is no
longer there so we live in a world where
even a small company can have hundreds
of different servers or different
services running all across different
parts of the world and in order to be
able to understand what's going on it's
actually mandatory for you to aggregate
them into a centralized location
otherwise it's completely impossible to
do it how much data can be gathered per
day and by how many sources it really
depends I mean we have customer sending
us 20 50 gigabyte today we have
customers sending us 15 terabytes a day
it really depends on on the type of
customer that we're working with and
that the size of the company
one thing we also realize that
when we first started working we had a
theory of this is gonna be mainly for
cloud based application companies that
are more innovative and we see today
that that basically runs across the
words we have pharmaceutical companies
that are completely not in the cloud we
have manufacturing companies we have IOT
devices that ship logs and Logan oolitic
is a it is really a multitasker that you
can do a lot with it and I think this is
a big reason for the success of this
domain in the IT operation and IT
analytic space
how long do those logs need to be stored
for it really depends some people save
it for two weeks some people save it for
90 days some people save it for five
years a lot of it depends on the
regulatory environment people live in
usually for production issues if you
haven't looked into it in two weeks
they're either not interesting or
they're continue to happen again and you
can see them happening over and over
again so usually two weeks is is I would
say two weeks to thirty days is the most
common use case that we see does that
affect the machine learning portion nope
because the machine learning portion is
actually because we're not looking at
the data the machine learning is running
in real-time on the logs as they get in
so the moment we detect an issue then we
we highlight it to you in any of two so
I I also want to send a little bit more
externally a bit more about the machine
learning so the usual process that
someone does today and and I'm also a
developer so I've done the same thing
the people the today is usually Iran and
you're using a lot of open-source
products and you're using products that
like you're not an expert and nobody can
no organization can be an expert in all
the products and you see an exception in
your load data then the system is
working fine I mean you see an exception
in MySQL or in Kafka or in elasticsearch
and things work work okay
I mean until they don't and then
you look at it and what is the first
thing you do you google the exception or
you google the error you're good at
Google the message it you couldn't
figure out what it is and guess what it
happened to other people before you and
the thing they type into other before
you you start reading about it and
sometimes it's something that you can
fix it's a small configuration something
you use it wrong sometimes maybe to
record a version upgrade it's a very
common thing that that people I mean
environments run with issues in them
that nobody is is checking and what
we're doing is we're continuously
checking for all the possible errors and
we're gonna give you kind of like the
best the best solution that we have in
order for you to start digging into the
problem and understanding what it is so
as part of the system you
programmatically are querying these
other resources like Stack Overflow
forums where other people might have
reported an issue right correct
so we're programmatically looking to all
of them and instead of you running into
an issue and searching for it in stock
overflow we search that overflow and we
bring two issues to you because at the
end of the day all of the log analytics
systems that exist today the value you
can get out of it is limited by the
question that you can ask so if you know
that there is an issue in your search
for it you will find it and it's great
value but how do you know that there
aren't issue you're not aware of that
nobody reported on to you so this is
what we do and we highlight all the
issues that we have based on our
analysis of things that happen and
discussion that happen across the world
and and we basically bring this to you
we start your data in real time for all
the issues before we talk more about
this integration with machine learning
and human insights from forums and other
platforms I want to understand the
machine learning portion in log analysis
what machine learning techniques are
useful for this
so I think one of the most useful
machine learning is cluster ization and
being able to understand the two
different threads talk about one same
issue we also have classifiers that are
running the third job is to be able to
say okay this issue is this is the
signature in the log if you found this
this is the description it talks about
that product there is a solution here
this is a high severity or low severity
or medium severity so there's
classifiers that run and and be able to
do it
clustering information like I said and
also machine learning to understand out
of I mean we have no more than 60 or 70
thousand different signature how do we
ask sixty thousand questions on every
log line that comes in if customers send
us terabytes and terabytes a day
what's the realistic way and how do we
build kind of like an engine that
searching it and real time let's talk
about clustering first when you apply to
log analysis what are examples of
clusters then can be identified like I
want to understand I have logs from
Windows for example in what does one
cluster look like so this is the the
question of clustering so the clustering
is applied in two different dimension
one of them is understanding the
clustering the log data itself and the
other one is clustering the different
discussions that we graph from the
public domain into a single kind of
issue into a single insight we call them
so clustering of log data itself this is
a this is a great feature and and what
it does is to be able to say okay logs
from it from the same log type are most
likely in the same cluster and then we
run and some people run like different
distances our algorithm to be able to
detect how how far is different looks
from one another and then we do some
pattern
matching and say okay which part of the
log line is standard which one is
changing how do we extract the changing
part of it and we we cluster all the
same log lines together yes what I'm
thinking more is I've seen clustering
but in other examples like marketing
like here's the cluster of people that
tend to like Hollywood movies and we
found this other cluster of people that
watch other type of movies and things
like that so I want to understand in the
logs what exactly does a cluster mean so
let me give you an example I mean let's
say you are running you're running a
website and you're sending old all the
excess data from your website so this
data comes in and every message includes
the IP address which came from the
response code whether it's 200 which
means okay or there is an error or
something like that how long it took the
message to process which URL was was
being accessed in your website and the
first clustering is to be able to
collaborate by the actual type saying
okay these are all logs from the same
time the second clustering is being able
to differentiate and say I'm gonna group
all the logs that have the same response
together and I'm gonna work the logs
that have different response in in a
different group so that's one clustering
that's being done but the other
clustering that we use is the actual
clustering on the threads that are that
we're crawling so if we see a thread
let's talk about a product let's say we
see a thread it talks about
elasticsearch and talk about a specific
issue there are probably 10 other
threads that are talking about the same
issue and how do we group them together
and say all these discussions basically
relate to the same problem they relate
to the same product they relate to the
same product version and that's kind of
like how we group them together and how
we pick the best one out of them how we
say okay out of all the discussion that
we've seen on a certain problem this is
probably the most helpful one because it
has more discussions it has an answer in
it the person who asked the question
acknowledges that the issue
was addressed and and that's kind of
like how we cluster and clustered the
discussions so there are two parts of
clustering like you're saying one is
done to the logs itself and the other
one is done to this human insight
component which is answers on forums
Stack Overflow and things like that
correct so it's very similar to what you
said about okay let's find out all the
discussions of people that are
interested in a specific movie so we
found all we find all the discussion
that are people that are interested in a
specific product and then we find all
the discussion where people are
interested in a specific product on a
specific issue in that product and
that's kind of like how we group the
discussions together and that's kind of
like where the value is and where the
algorithm stands
this podcast is supported by atlanticnet
hosting solution provider of healthcare
HIPAA PCI compliance and ad tech if
you're feeling the pain of having
outdated technology call atlanticnet and
get the latest security firewall
intrusion detection backup disaster
recovery and virtualization or if you're
starting a new project are not getting
the results you want from your current
providers atlanticnet can help you
succeed
the fully audited solutions in 23 years
in business they won't let you down
visit atlanticnet to learn more ok let's
talk about the the classifier component
can you explain a little bit more what
this classifiers are classifying yeah so
so what they do is they basically go
through each one of the discussions and
understanding first of all which product
are are we talking about what's the
problem in the product what's the
quality what's the tone that people are
using in order to describe the problem
how severe it is and that's kind of like
what they do the extracted product they
expect to extract the issue out of it
and that's kind of like how they
classify the information is this more
when the logs come with a human
component for example they add a
description that a human wrote and you
might want to detect how critical it is
or how severe it is this is part of our
scanning the discussions that people
talk about the logs and understanding
how severe the discussion is based on it
how severe the problem is yeah which
product are they talking about that's
kind of like how we how we use that so
these are classifiers again in the human
insight yeah do you have classifiers for
the logs themselves we do not have
classifiers for the logs themselves we
like I said I think what the way we run
things is we our whole algorithm is very
similar to how for example Google ranks
his pages and say what's more relevant
when you run a search we rank
the logs based on what other people
found to be relevant so we give you the
relevance of what's actually interesting
in the log file not based on the data
that you have but based on what other
people thought is interesting in their
log data and we're in the loop are
humans still necessary in the log
analysis humans are always necessary and
one other component in this algorithm is
the supervision so we run supervised
machine learning which means that when
we present a customer what the insight
is and I'd say oK we've seen this
exception and it's high severity talks
about Kafka and the here here are a few
threads to talk about it we measure the
interaction of that user with the
insight and if he says you know what
it's not really interesting or yeah it's
very interesting or you talk about a
different product that creates the
supervision engine and that's how we can
basically improve both the classifiers
and and the clustering algorithms so as
I am understanding this the machine
learning portion is more focused on the
component that humans still do a lot for
example querying on Stack Overflow so
what you're trying to do is making that
shorter the tasks that humans do right
yeah what we do is two things first of
all making the tacit you mean the
shorter and also you said I mean you
know what to search for based on what
you know to search and what we do is we
bring all the searches anyone has ever
done in the world and searching your
load data so we make it both accessible
and easy to do and you mentioned before
that you're using supervised learning
right yeah how much data is necessary to
train the algorithm
so we run it on a periodic basis and try
and retrain the algorithm the algorithm
all the time obviously you need quite a
lot of data and this is why it's it's a
continuous project and a continuous
effort to and to be able to improvement
and a component of supervised learning
involves like I said having the training
data which already has labels in this
case what does the training data looks
like is it about this post was relevant
or not relevant was it relevant not
relevant what is the severity of it is
there an issue in it which product are
we talking about which version of the
product are we talking about
and so we're trying to do these are all
the features and and we learned from how
the humans interact with it and saying
hey wow this was wrong and that means ok
let's go back to and try retrain the
algorithm now on the same data he needs
to find something else and that's
basically how it works
whose labeling the training data we're
labeling all the training data based on
the algorithm that that we have and the
users of our systems are continuously
labeling the training data so this is
the algorithm Ron and comes up with
insights and all the features on top of
it and then we present this to all of
our customers and all of our users and
they change or not change the data based
on their understanding and that goes
back into being the training data for
the other written back again so the
labeling portion is submitted in the in
the user interface are now kind of
analogous to capture right ok yeah yeah
you've worked with logs and log analysis
and you've probably seen different
formats of logs should we change our
logs to better serve a machine learning
system I don't know I mean it's a good
it's a good question I think that it's
very hard to be able to enforce
different logging type especially since
today you were using so many open-source
components that there
structure and the way they write to the
log is decided by the person who
developed that open source product so
being able to force a structure to be
able to do this I think is it's gonna be
very hard to task one thing that I saw
mentioned on Lux IO
post is that most of the log data is
meaningless
what portion of the data can be used by
machine learning algorithms most of the
log data is meaningless and this is why
we're not looking at the data and what
we look at when we look at kind of like
discussions and how people interact with
data we find it a very very small
percentage of the log data is actually
relevant so this is this is kind of like
our our analysis from it is this because
we're currently over logging information
or yeah I think we're definitely over
logging because we don't we do not want
to be in a situation where there is an
issue and we do not have enough
information to troubleshoot it
so we're differently over voguing most
log lines are just saved to a father are
never being read by anyone because they
don't represent any any issues but you
want them there in case there is issue
to be able to troubleshoot to go back
and understand what happened let's talk
a little more about the combining
machine learning with human insights for
for that what part do you take from a
log and decide to query for it in other
platforms for human insights so we take
and we start from the actual human
insights so we look at we look at the
threads that people do and we try to
find their pieces of log data so part of
the classifiers the way
yeah we're not looking at people's blogs
not people's logs but
let's say I have my system and I have
all this files of logs do you start
programmatically looking at these logs
and then connecting them with the human
insight we what we do is we we have like
a pretty big library of all the human
insights and we continuously match every
log iran against all the insights that
we have in the system so that that's
what we do but we do not look at the log
and try to find insights from there okay
so you look at the insights and you try
to find those in the logs yeah okay so
this sounds like you have a big library
of human insights that you've gathered
are the systems that you work with or
the companies are they similar enough
that they can share a library of human
insights for issues yeah because that
that library is is big enough and it
scans across tens if not hundreds of
different discussion places and that's
that's the power of it I mean we really
believe that with the world is become so
dynamic that that's basically the only
way to be able to keep track of issues
that you have in the system by doing
that it doesn't only pertain to
operational issues and exceptions in the
law of I mean some of it is security
insight because we went through a
security forum and they talk about all
the if you find this in your log file
that means that someone's trying to do a
cross-site scripting with you on your
website or someone's gonna do trying to
hack into your website or you get a
password that someone's trying to hack
and and all of these things are are all
documented on the web so we we quote
growth of all of them and there's
definitely a high degree of correlation
between our customers and for the
classifiers that you run on the human
insights sources do you know what those
classifiers are just basic kind of
classifiers to be able to detect
the issuances mostly proprietary
information that we've developed
in-house okay yeah that's what I was
wondering what problems do you think
need to be solved to have even less
human intervention in log analysis it's
a good question I think one of the
problems to be solved is the automatic
data parsing so what we've talked about
in the beginning being able to to
cluster and understand log structure
saying okay these ten million logs are
the same the same structure and this is
the parameters in them and this is the
fixed part this is a big thing that is
being developed and this is definitely
going to help and remove them reduce the
human interaction with them I think that
there's always gonna be an expert
involved and there is always gonna be
someone who is gonna need to look at how
things work the person who actually
wrote the system I think the other thing
which I also wanted to say is that our
mission and what we're trying to do is
we're not trying to find all the
problems that exist in your system but
when we tell you that there is a problem
what we're trying to do is that the
system is going to be accurate and
there's actually a problem and that
insight is actually relevant for what
you're looking for because the biggest
challenge with IT environment is the
whole concept of noise to value ratio
because if you have a lot of noise and
your system just grows and grows all the
time because the company is successful
and you get more business and more
developers are adding more features and
functions then you stop relying it
because all your seer is noise and we
give you a very kind of like a surgical
understanding of things that we think
are the most important things you can
look for in your log data and and
addressing them is is it gonna address a
problem before it happens you don't need
to wait for an anomaly detection telling
you that there is some sort of an
anomaly because you see an error in the
log file that says that you're using the
wrong configuration on a specific
product how effective have you found
that the ins
it's that you give the users from their
logs are
I think we found it to be very extremely
effective we got a lot of feedback from
customers that hey you highlight an
issue I had no idea existed in my system
which is what we're doing
I can tell you some things that we've
discovered about ourselves I can tell
you one for example we had really really
early on when we first started a company
a bunch of issues with elasticsearch it
was like a very old version of
elasticsearch and we spent probably
about a month this is kind of like way
before we we've developed the insights
and we couldn't understand what's going
on why is it disconnecting and why is it
happening and then we kind of launched
the insights and we discovered that
there is when the when the servers and
the machines restart there is one log
line it's saying
SKB ride the rocket which is a scatter
gather configuration on Ubuntu on the
specific version that we're using and
apparently there were a lot of
discussion about it that it has adverse
effect on elasticsearch clusters so we
could have like gone through the logs
for another two months and add more
resources and change machine types and
change elasticsearch versions and we
would have never found it and just by
understanding that log line and it it
wasn't it completely unrelated
locational so it's not the log line
appear when the system start it does not
appear when the problem happens but just
detecting it and being able to analyze
it proved to be very very valuable to us
we find we found customer with issues in
kubernetes the way they configure it
that they say they came back say hey
thanks I mean we we had no idea this
existed in our system and we've been
trying to chase an issue in a completely
different location for weeks now we have
customer that we found hardware issues
in their environments and nobody
bothered to look for it because who
would think that there is a memory card
that is not functioning in one of the
server and yes it's in the log files but
out of terabytes of data a day who's
gonna find that one low blind it says I
restarted the server and I have an issue
in my memory card so so far
and again this is as you can imagine
this algorithm in this system is an
evolving system but so far with the
evidence we have we have a lot of proof
of saying it's extremely valuable
because it it does help you find
associations and places where it might
not be obvious for example when I'm
debugging or looking at logs I go and
start where the failure was where the
log of the failure and then go from
there but like you said it might just be
some other some other aspect during
restart yeah correct
I mean it so might be some other aspects
something that happen in the system and
it lets you know about things that
happen before they they become an issue
and you say this is an insight I'm gonna
go and investigate what it means and we
give you the beginning of the
investigation which is a few discussion
that people talk about it and you can
say okay let me read it
maybe it's relevant maybe I'm using the
wrong version and if I just upgrade this
problem is gonna go away maybe this
problem is not that critical and it's
okay that it happens well Asaf thank you
for coming on software engineering radio
was great talking to you thank you very
much thanks for having me
users want a simple way to pay you want
an easy integration Braintree allows you
to accept nearly any payment type from
almost any device with just one
integration it's flexible to your
systems needs and supports most
programming languages and when your
checkout is simpler and faster you're
going to have happier customers that's
what we call a win-win
learn more at Braintree payments comm
/se radio
thanks for listening to deci radio an
educational program brought to you by
out your police software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening